<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>smallyu‘s Blog</title>
  <icon>https://en.smallyu.net/favicon.png</icon>
  <subtitle>smallyu&#39;s Blog</subtitle>
  <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub"/>
  <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/"/>
  <updated>2024-06-03T16:03:04.852Z</updated>
  <id>https://en.smallyu.net/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>smallyu</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>PBFT in Blockchain Doesn&#39;t Require a Second Vote</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/06/03/PBFT%20in%20Blockchain%20Doesn&#39;t%20Require%20a%20Second%20Vote/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/06/03/PBFT%20in%20Blockchain%20Doesn&#39;t%20Require%20a%20Second%20Vote/</id>
    <published>2024-06-03T03:09:21.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-03T16:03:04.852Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why does PBFT require two rounds of voting, and what is the role of the second vote? This question has puzzled me for a long time.</p><h3 id="Reverse-Deduction"><a href="#Reverse-Deduction" class="headerlink" title="Reverse Deduction"></a>Reverse Deduction</h3><p>From this perspective, in what situations does the second vote play a role? It only plays a role when the results of the second vote differ from the first. If the second vote’s results are strictly consistent with the first, then there is no need for a second vote.</p><p>So, in what situations would the second vote’s results differ from the first? Only when malicious nodes exist and deliberately cast different votes in the second voting phase will the results differ.</p><p>This is the conventional operational flowchart of traditional PBFT, where node 3 is a faulty or malicious node and does not respond from beginning to end:</p><img src="1.png" width="70%"><p>This is the flowchart with the prepare phase removed, retaining only one voting process, where node 3 is still a faulty node and does not respond:</p><img src="2.png" width="60%"><p>The key is that in this scenario, nodes 0, 1, and 2 are honest nodes and will never cast malicious votes or abstain, so the result of the commit phase will be consistent with the prepare phase. Thus, even if the prepare phase is removed, the system will eventually reach a consensus.</p><p>Node 3 has always been a malicious node. If, during the commit phase, any of the nodes 0, 1, or 2 cast votes that differ from the prepare phase, it means that there are more than one malicious node in the system, exceeding the fault tolerance capability.</p><h3 id="Forward-Understanding"><a href="#Forward-Understanding" class="headerlink" title="Forward Understanding"></a>Forward Understanding</h3><p>To prove that the second vote is necessary is equivalent to stating that without the second vote, the system will not function correctly.</p><p>Logically, even if the second vote has various benefits, such as increasing the system’s fault tolerance through redundancy, quickly identifying errors, and promptly adjusting to a consistent state, it does not prove that the second vote is indispensable. For example, in the high-voted answer in <a href="https://cs.stackexchange.com/questions/54152/why-is-the-commit-phase-in-pbft-necessary">Why is the commit phase in PBFT necessary?</a>, many points are mentioned, but it mainly explains the design and function of the commit phase from a positive perspective.</p><p>A more plausible explanation I’ve found is here: <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/51125238/pbft-why-cant-the-replicas-perform-the-request-after-2-3-have-prepared-why-do">PBFT: Why can’t the replicas perform the request after 2&#x2F;3 have prepared? Why do we need the commit phase?</a> </p><p>It mentions that without the commit phase, nodes cannot ensure the order of request execution during a view change.</p><p>I think the description on StackOverflow differs from the meaning of the high-voted answer. The high-voted answer implies that nodes’ execute phases become inconsistent without the commit phase, with some being faster and others slower. However, even with two rounds of voting, nodes might fail after the commit phase but before execution, causing execution differences. Therefore, this type of failure is not the critical scenario.</p><p>A more reasonable scenario is mentioned in the paper <a href="https://pmg.csail.mit.edu/papers/bft-tocs.pdf">Practical Byzantine Fault Tolerance and Proactive Recovery</a>. During a view change, different requests might use the same sequence number and be packaged into different views.</p><blockquote><p>Replicas may collect prepared certificates in different views with the same sequence number and different requests. The commit phase solves this problem as follows.</p></blockquote><h3 id="Single-Vote-Process"><a href="#Single-Vote-Process" class="headerlink" title="Single Vote Process"></a>Single Vote Process</h3><p>This scenario is based on a single vote process, meaning there is no prepare phase.</p><h4 id="Scenario-Setup"><a href="#Scenario-Setup" class="headerlink" title="Scenario Setup"></a>Scenario Setup</h4><p><strong>View V1</strong></p><ol><li>R1 proposes proposal P and broadcasts it to R2, R3, and R4.</li><li>Proposal P is executed by R2, R3, and R4, but not by R1.</li></ol><pre><code>R1: –R2: P –&gt; Execute PR3: P –&gt; Execute PR4: P –&gt; Execute P</code></pre><p><strong>View Switch to V2</strong></p><ol><li>Assume R1 fails, and the view switches to V2.</li><li>R2 proposes a new proposal P’.</li><li>R2 proposes a new proposal P’ and broadcasts it to R1, R3, and R4.</li><li>The new proposal P’ is executed by all replicas.</li></ol><pre><code>R1: --      P&#39; --&gt; Execute P&#39;R2: P --&gt; Execute P      P&#39; --&gt; Execute P&#39;R3: P --&gt; Execute P      P&#39; --&gt; Execute P&#39;R4: P --&gt; Execute P      P&#39; --&gt; Execute P&#39;</code></pre><h4 id="Specific-Example"><a href="#Specific-Example" class="headerlink" title="Specific Example"></a>Specific Example</h4><p>Assume proposals P and P’ are operations on the same account balance:</p><ul><li>Proposal P: Increase account A’s balance by 10 units.</li><li>Proposal P’: Decrease account A’s balance by 5 units.</li></ul><p>The order of operations and results in views V1 and V2 are as follows:</p><p><strong>View V1</strong></p><pre><code>R1: Account A balance = 100 (P not executed)R2: Account A balance = 110 (P executed)R3: Account A balance = 110 (P executed)R4: Account A balance = 110 (P executed)</code></pre><p><strong>View V2</strong></p><pre><code>R1: Account A balance = 100 (P not executed) –&gt; Execute P’ –&gt; Account A balance = 95R2: Account A balance = 110 (P executed) –&gt; Execute P’ –&gt; Account A balance = 105R3: Account A balance = 110 (P executed) –&gt; Execute P’ –&gt; Account A balance = 105R4: Account A balance = 110 (P executed) –&gt; Execute P’ –&gt; Account A balance = 105</code></pre><h4 id="Scenario-Analysis"><a href="#Scenario-Analysis" class="headerlink" title="Scenario Analysis"></a>Scenario Analysis</h4><p>Let’s repeat this sentence: Different requests (R2) use the same sequence number (R1 thinks it is P) and are packaged into different views (P’). The same sequence number should refer to the execution order, indicating which request is to be executed at the current time.</p><p>In the above scenario, the final state is indeed inconsistent due to node A’s failure.</p><h3 id="Two-Votes"><a href="#Two-Votes" class="headerlink" title="Two Votes"></a>Two Votes</h3><p>How does the two-vote process solve the problem in the above scenario?</p><ol><li>If node A fails after receiving the prepare result and before starting the commit, all nodes will not enter the execute phase.</li><li>If node A fails after receiving the commit result and before starting the execute, node A will retry executing P based on the commit result, then execute P’.</li></ol><h4 id="Scenario-Analysis-1"><a href="#Scenario-Analysis-1" class="headerlink" title="Scenario Analysis"></a>Scenario Analysis</h4><p>Did you notice a bit of unfairness in point 2?</p><p>In the two-vote scenario, node A can retry executing P based on the commit result.</p><p>In the single-vote scenario, node A does not retry executing P based on the commit result but directly executes P’.</p><p>Therefore, the two-vote process does not completely avoid state inconsistencies caused by node failures before execution. It merely adds an extra communication step to repeatedly confirm that other nodes’ states are consistent with its expectations, reducing the risk of state inconsistency.</p><p>The two-vote process advances the time for detecting faults. If node A does not cast a vote in the commit phase, other nodes will know that node A has failed, rather than waiting until they have executed and then discovering that node A has not executed. More confirmation means more security, reducing the cost of system rollback after execution and trying to agree as much as possible before execution. This is probably the greatest role of the two-vote process.</p><p>Overall, the second vote never seems to demonstrate an indispensable significance but merely brings some benefits and enhances system security. This issue might be similar to why TCP requires three-way handshakes to establish a connection. Wouldn’t two be enough? Perhaps even one is sufficient, but it could cause some problems. Three confirmations are sufficiently secure.</p><h3 id="Stateless-vs-Stateful"><a href="#Stateless-vs-Stateful" class="headerlink" title="Stateless vs. Stateful"></a>Stateless vs. Stateful</h3><p>Why does PBFT require repeated confirmations to avoid state inconsistencies after execution? Maybe because any system rollback is a very cautious task, so the cost of communication before execution is increased.</p><h4 id="Stateless"><a href="#Stateless" class="headerlink" title="Stateless"></a>Stateless</h4><p>Returning to the single-vote scenario above, under what circumstances would the faulty node A not execute P’?</p><ol><li>Node A knows it failed to execute P.</li><li>Node A must execute P before executing P’.</li></ol><p>If these two conditions are met, even with a single vote, the same effect as the two-vote process can be achieved.</p><p>For stateless systems, if a node only records a final number, it would be quite difficult. The node knows it has not executed P and then receives a P’, but cannot distinguish whether P’ should be executed after P or is on an equal level with P.</p><p>The normal sequence is:</p><pre><code>O -&gt; P -&gt; P&#39;</code></pre><p>For node A, knowing it has not executed P but receives a P’:</p><pre><code>O -&gt; (P&#39;)?</code></pre><p>Should it execute? Node A does, and the state becomes chaotic.</p><p>For this reason, the execution in stateless systems is very cautious.</p><h4 id="Stateful"><a href="#Stateful" class="headerlink" title="Stateful"></a>Stateful</h4><p>Blockchain is a stateful system that naturally records its execution records (blocks) and enforces the ordering of requests (block hash, parent hash).</p><p>When a node receives a block, it can determine the position of the block, whether it should be executed in the current round, and whether it is missing blocks, promptly synchronizing the blocks from other nodes.</p><p>Therefore, in the context of blockchain, if the goal is merely to achieve the final state consistency of most nodes, a second vote is not necessary.</p><h3 id="Doubts"><a href="#Doubts" class="headerlink" title="Doubts"></a>Doubts</h3><p>Why does PBFT require two votes? This question lies at the knowledge boundary of GPT-4. If you ask it in detail, it will start making up answers, which is typical of GPT-4 when it does not know the answer.</p><p>With my limited internet search capabilities, I have never found a convincing reason that proves the second vote in PBFT is necessary.</p><p>After repeated deductions, the conclusion I have reached is that a second vote is not necessary, and a single vote can also achieve the same majority node consistency.</p><p>But why, for so long, have PBFT and various variants such as Tendermint and HotStuff retained the two-vote process? Why has no one ever questioned the necessity of the second vote?</p><p>Where exactly am I wrong? Perhaps my understanding of PBFT is not deep enough, and I have not touched upon the scenarios where the second vote truly plays a role. But if such scenarios exist, why can’t I find material that directly describes these scenarios?</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why does PBFT require two rounds of voting, and what is the role of the second vote? This question has puzzled me for a long</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="BFT" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/BFT/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Developer&#39;s Mindset</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/05/30/Developer&#39;s%20Mindset/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/05/30/Developer&#39;s%20Mindset/</id>
    <published>2024-05-30T05:46:26.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-04T04:00:50.804Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Prelude: “<a href="https://www.yinwang.org/blog-cn/2015/02/01/creative-thinking">Creative Thinking</a>“ — Wang Yin</p><hr><p>I’ve noticed a phenomenon: when you say A is good, someone will say A is not as good as B, so A is not good.</p><p>The first case is when you say SOL’s technology is better than BNB’s, it will spark controversy. Some people use the fact that SOL has experienced several outages to prove that SOL’s technology is not good. Others say that trading coins is not technology-driven but capital-driven, and that technology is not important. These viewpoints reflect their respective positions.</p><p>From a developer’s perspective, no one would regard BNB as a blockchain because it is a platform coin, with centralized node operations and an operational model that is not blockchain-like. Technically, it forked Geth’s code with some modifications, and adopted PoS earlier than Geth to increase control over the entire chain. After ETH completes the Cancun upgrade, BNB also imitated and implemented its own BIP-4844, clearly belonging to the same technical system as ETH.</p><p>Another perspective is that after ETH’s ETF is close to approval, people start discussing whether the next ETF will be for DOGE, SOL, or even DOT, but no one mentions BNB, which fully demonstrates that BNB is different from other public chains and not in the same track. To determine whether two products belong to the same track, one can see if there is a competitive relationship where one must die for the other to live. If BNB uses ETH’s technology but hopes ETH dies, it is illogical. The normal logic should be hoping ETH gets better, and BNB will also benefit.</p><p>From a user’s (trader’s) perspective, it doesn’t matter what technology you use or how good your technology is. A meme can be in the top ten in market value, a dog with a hat can be worth billions, I will go where the investors are, I will buy what capital speculates, FOMO is the way to go.</p><p>The second case is when you say SOL’s technology is good, others will say ETH is better, so SOL is not good.</p><p>It’s the same issue of perspective. From a user’s point of view, there are countless reasons to compare the pros and cons of two projects. When you say A is good, someone can always find a B that is better than A or a C that is better than A in some aspect. Using such techniques, they can defeat anyone or any project. There is also a huge space for controversy and a hierarchy of disdain, just like whether PHP is the best language in the world.</p><p>But from a developer’s perspective, if I want to develop a chain, my chain needs to compare technology and compete for the market with SOL. Can I do better than SOL? Certainly not. So, from this standpoint, isn’t it reasonable for me to say SOL’s technology is pretty good?</p><p>SOL here is just an example. Actually, any established public chain in the top 100 of CMC has some highlights, especially those that pioneered and tried different consensus algorithms. They may not be as well-known as ETH and SOL, but they have also achieved good results.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Prelude: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yinwang.org/blog-cn/2015/02/01/creative-thinking&quot;&gt;Creative Thinking&lt;/a&gt;“ — Wang Yin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Mindset" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/Mindset/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Key Points of Issuing Cryptocurrency</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/05/26/Key%20Points%20of%20Issuing%20Cryptocurrency/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/05/26/Key%20Points%20of%20Issuing%20Cryptocurrency/</id>
    <published>2024-05-26T14:31:26.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-04T04:05:06.270Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First, here are two additional tips about investing in cryptocurrencies:</p><ol><li><p>Whether you are using Bitcoin, fiat currency, or another cryptocurrency as your base, it mainly depends on what you have on hand and which currency is easily accessible. The logic of having no silver bullet applies in any situation.</p></li><li><p>With ETH’s ETF halfway approved, it implies that the SEC might accept PoS, but the ETF funds cannot be used for staking (I still don’t understand why). Previously, I mentioned selecting from the top 100 on CMC, and it might need another condition: the cryptocurrency should not have been labeled as a security by the SEC. Maybe after personnel changes or new laws pass, cryptocurrencies will no longer be under the SEC’s jurisdiction. However, at least it shows that under the same standards, many cryptocurrencies have obvious problems. ETH has always been in an ambiguous state, so its current situation with the ETF is quite complicated.</p></li></ol><p>There are actually only a handful of safe and reliable cryptocurrencies. For example, DOT has a low profile, and the SEC has never defined DOT, but its staking rate has reached 57% of its circulation, maintaining an annual yield of 17%. I still can’t understand what this situation implies, what the consequences of a high staking rate are, and why DOT’s yield can be so high. If all holders receive the annual yield equally, wouldn’t it be equivalent to inflation, causing the price to drop? For the network, the higher the staking rate, the safer it is. However, the fewer coins in circulation, the less useful the coin is, and it cannot even be used for transaction fees. Such incomprehensible cryptocurrencies are also not worth buying.</p><p>Now, about issuing cryptocurrencies. Recently, I inadvertently listened to a recording of Li Xiaolai that was circulating online, and it was quite enlightening.</p><p>The core point of all cryptocurrencies is just one: to distribute the coins in a valuable way. The price of the coin is determined by what the holders believe it is worth. As long as holders do not sell, the price will not fall. Including BTC, it is distributed through mining, every 10 minutes, a fixed amount regardless of how many participants, with one winner every 10 minutes, adding randomness and encouraging active participation.</p><p>ETH is also distributed through mining, with block rewards every 12 seconds given to miners, similar to BTC. ETH’s two major black marks are:</p><ol><li>The development team pre-mined an unknown amount, and the ICO distributed tokens at a low price to many people in a black-box manner.</li><li>The unlimited issuance model, with no cap on the total supply, potentially causing inflation and implying that the development team can print money continuously.</li></ol><p>Li Xiaolai issued a coin called Caddy, collaborating with a community of millions of real users, selling it to them at one-tenth the price and encouraging them to like, share, and hype news online. Li Xiaolai himself said that to successfully plan a coin, being an influencer with traffic and influence is a crucial condition. Li Xiaolai, being an influencer, frequently publishes books, gives speeches, and is a well-known teacher at New Oriental, has a strong background.</p><p>The point about being an influencer ultimately attracts a large number of fans, who recognize the coin, and the coin reaches these fans at a certain price. Therefore, whether it’s mining, early airdrops, exchange LaunchPools, or incentive distributions, the goal is to distribute the coins to holders in a valuable way. Holders must pay a price for the coin to have value. Giving it away broadly for free makes the coin worthless, but pegging it one-to-one with the dollar makes it a stablecoin. This value must be controlled, neither too specific nor non-existent.</p><p>Additionally, tenfold or hundredfold coins have no logic. ETH’s hype is generally attributed to two main reasons: one is a national policy at the time that prevented BTC from being withdrawn from exchanges. The other is a Ponzi scheme using ETH with a daily interest rate of 1%, where many users bought ETH from exchanges and transferred it to the Ponzi scheme, driving up the price. Interestingly, during this period, ETH’s price increased by over a thousand times, and the Ponzi scheme could sustain itself for three years without collapsing.</p><p>FIL was once heavily mined in China, with its price soaring to 200. Why was the price so high? It was also due to a Ponzi scheme. Later, mining was banned in China, and now FIL has no vitality left, despite its genuinely good technology. Another example is NEO, which also rose by hundreds of times without a good technical foundation, having only a dozen centralized nodes and being written in C#, claiming to be the Chinese version of Ethereum. The main reason for its rise was also a financial scheme. The founders didn’t hold many coins, and even now, it’s evident that the coin price is periodically manipulated by the scheme.</p><p>So, technology is not the absolute priority. Technology serves as a basis for horizontal comparison. For instance, among several projects called ETA, ETB, ETC, and ETH, even a Ponzi scheme would choose a relatively reliable coin with something to hype. Then it’s up to fate.</p><p>As for gossip, many news reports state that Li Xiaolai was once the richest person in the crypto world, buying six-figure amounts of Bitcoin at a quarter of the market price, holding it for years through multiple bull and bear cycles, and finally selling it at a high price. But it’s not that simple. You can find many of Li Xiaolai’s Bitcoin lectures online, showing that he did not just buy and hold but understood Bitcoin’s complex knowledge, gave lectures, and logically believed in Bitcoin before entering the crypto world. This teaches us not to buy blindly, but to look carefully before buying, not just buying a token with a nice code on the exchange or based on promotional articles. Those who genuinely make money have a deep logical foundation and do a lot of homework.</p><p>Another version of the gossip is that Li Xiaolai organized a Bitcoin fund, raising tens of thousands of Bitcoins for private investments in mining, exchanges, and stocks, which resulted in heavy losses, with many people losing money and forming a rights group. Later, he invested in EOS and made back the money, paying off the debts at a discount. Li Xiaolai boasted about having six-figure Bitcoins, but he didn’t. The police couldn’t find them during a search, and Li Xiaolai is still restricted from leaving the country. Who knows if he really has Bitcoins? If he does, he can’t be let out. This teaches us that no one gets rich by trading cryptocurrencies. Li Xiaolai was already wealthy, and despite that, he kept engaging in various operations, investing, and running funds. Making money always involves doing things, not expecting to get rich from trading cryptocurrencies by just buying and holding. Even those who participated in Li Xiaolai’s Bitcoin fund were skeptical about Bitcoin’s future value, with many dropping out along the way. So, what about now?</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First, here are two additional tips about investing in cryptocurrencies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether you are using Bitcoin, fiat currency,</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Cryptocurrency" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/Cryptocurrency/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Small Tips for Cryptocurrency Investment</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/05/04/Small%20Tips%20for%20Cryptocurrency%20Investment/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/05/04/Small%20Tips%20for%20Cryptocurrency%20Investment/</id>
    <published>2024-05-04T12:44:13.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-03T16:06:56.841Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="1-BTC-is-the-Industry-Baseline"><a href="#1-BTC-is-the-Industry-Baseline" class="headerlink" title="1. BTC is the Industry Baseline"></a>1. BTC is the Industry Baseline</h3><p>The existence of Bitcoin underpins the entire cryptocurrency industry. If Bitcoin were ever to be discredited, deemed unsafe, not decentralized, or valueless, the whole industry would collapse. Bitcoin has never been surpassed. In fact, except for Bitcoin, all other cryptocurrencies are altcoins, especially in the eyes of veteran miners who have experienced the era of Bitcoin alone. Altcoins started as Bitcoin imitators, trying to make certain changes, including Ethereum. Vitalik also dabbled with colored coins, started chains from PoW, and raised funds in China. Everything started from Bitcoin.</p><h3 id="2-PoW-is-Resilient"><a href="#2-PoW-is-Resilient" class="headerlink" title="2. PoW is Resilient"></a>2. PoW is Resilient</h3><p>Around April 12, 2024, due to multiple factors, generally believed to be due to skirmishes between two countries potentially leading to war, all cryptocurrencies fell by an average of about 20%. Binance’s Gainer leaderboard was entirely red, which can be simply referred to as the 412 incident.</p><p>Observing the price changes during this period, it is evident that PoW-based coins generally fell less than PoS-based coins. Led by BTC, Doge, LTC, BCH, ZEC, ETC, and ETHW all showed smaller declines. After all, PoW chains involve miners investing real computational power and hardware costs, making them reluctant to sell at low prices. PoS, on the other hand, involves staking a lot of money into servers, generating money from money, which comes relatively easily. ETH, DOT, ADA, COSMOS, and many others—about 50 of the top 100 on CMC—are PoS-based with staking functions.</p><h3 id="3-BTC-Standard"><a href="#3-BTC-Standard" class="headerlink" title="3. BTC Standard"></a>3. BTC Standard</h3><p>The basic logic of crypto trading is based on the BTC standard, meaning trading altcoins against Bitcoin’s rate. Suppose you initially have 1 BTC and believe Doge’s upcoming rise will outperform BTC. You convert BTC to Doge, wait for Doge to rise by 20%, and then convert all Doge back to BTC. Your BTC has now increased from 1 to 1.2. This is the essence of the BTC standard.</p><p>From then on, you will ignore market fluctuations, undeterred by bull or bear markets, focusing only on the amount of Bitcoin you have—be it 1, 1.2, or 0.8. Regardless of how BTC’s price changes against fiat, it will double every four years, dropping before rising again, achieving all-time highs repeatedly.</p><p>Trading based on fiat standards usually ends in losses, with many suffering significant losses. This specifically refers to spot trading; avoid contracts entirely.</p><h3 id="4-Choose-from-CMC-Top-100"><a href="#4-Choose-from-CMC-Top-100" class="headerlink" title="4. Choose from CMC Top 100"></a>4. Choose from CMC Top 100</h3><p>Focus as much as possible on coins ranked in the top 100 on Coin Market Cap (CMC) and select from these. The reasons are twofold: the probability of a severe crash is lower, and support from the ecosystem is better. Lower-ranked coins can pose issues like wallet incompatibility, making transactions difficult. Or, a contract address change (as happened recently with an AI sector coin) can leave you stuck, as the old contract still runs at 20% of the price, while the new one operates at 80%.</p><h3 id="5-Founder’s-Departure-Marks-Decentralization"><a href="#5-Founder’s-Departure-Marks-Decentralization" class="headerlink" title="5. Founder’s Departure Marks Decentralization"></a>5. Founder’s Departure Marks Decentralization</h3><p>BTC is unique because its founder remained anonymous from the start, which was a very smart move. This anonymity allowed BTC to be widely speculated upon. Why are there so many asset types on BTC, like colored coins, RGB++, Taproot Assets, inscriptions, runes, and L2 assets still competing? Because no one can come forward to define a roadmap for Bitcoin, and no one knows how it should develop next.</p><p>In contrast, ETH’s founder actively participates in global conferences and gives talks, outlining Ethereum’s roadmap and guiding L2’s technological direction. When ETH was attacked by hackers, the founder led the community to fork away the attack history and transitioned the consensus mechanism from PoW to PoS. Such influence shows that ETH is centralized. ETH cannot pass the Howey test and is likely to be classified as a security under SEC standards.</p><p>If you created a coin and promoted it, it would seem inappropriate. However, if a coin is decentralized, you can promote it freely. You just like Doge, you can promote it as you wish.</p><p>BSV’s CW also lost a lawsuit this year. Some in the community see this as positive, believing CW’s departure signifies BSV becoming truly community-driven. Regardless of BSV’s future, the departure of the founder is a significant indicator.</p><p>Another example is ETC and ETHW. Both were forked by Baory, a controversial figure, but their market value, price, and TVL are notable. During the 412 incident, these two coins showed resilience. Although buying them is risky due to lack of technical updates and low GitHub activity, their prices remain intriguing. ETC and ETHW are truly without founders and are PoW coins.</p><p>Additionally, since Ethereum transitioned from PoW to PoS, the ETH&#x2F;BTC exchange rate has been declining, from nearly 0.1 to around 0.05 now.</p><h3 id="6-Others"><a href="#6-Others" class="headerlink" title="6. Others"></a>6. Others</h3><p>Let’s take a simple comparison of the CMC top 10:</p><ol><li>BTC: Industry baseline, market cap dominance of 50%</li><li>ETH: Creator of EVM and DeFi market, with a vast ecosystem, market cap dominance of 16%</li><li>USDT: The most widely used stablecoin, backed by US Treasury reserves</li><li>BNB: The largest exchange platform token</li><li>SOL: PoH+DPoS consensus mechanism, centralized, relies on a few sequencers to order transactions before handing them to validators for packaging</li><li>USDC: The safest stablecoin, backed by gold reserves</li><li>XRP: RPCA consensus mechanism</li><li>DOGE: PoW consensus, the largest meme coin, favored by Musk</li><li>TON: Chain issued by Telegram</li><li>ADA: Founded by a famous figure, developed using Haskell, UTXO + PoS</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-BTC-is-the-Industry-Baseline&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-BTC-is-the-Industry-Baseline&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;1. BTC is the Industry</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Crypto Trading" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/Crypto-Trading/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Why PoW is More Decentralized than PoS</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/04/14/Why%20PoW%20is%20More%20Decentralized%20than%20PoS/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/04/14/Why%20PoW%20is%20More%20Decentralized%20than%20PoS/</id>
    <published>2024-04-13T16:50:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-06T12:54:09.711Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to compare PoW and PoS from the perspective of entry barriers.</p><p>We often describe a blockchain as either permissionless or permissioned. This means whether becoming a block-producing node requires authorization or not.</p><p>PoW is universally recognized as a consensus mechanism that does not require authorization for mining. As long as you have a computer, you can join the network and start mining. If you can compute the required hash value, even if done manually, you have the right to produce blocks, and you decide which transactions to include in those blocks. Whether you can compute it is another matter.</p><p>BFT is a typical consensus mechanism that requires authorization. Many projects using BFT-like consensus directly require a CA center to issue certificates, and only nodes with certificates can undertake mining responsibilities in the network. The reason why the CA center issues a certificate to you is entirely an offline action. The authority to become a block-producing node is firmly controlled by the CA center.</p><p>There is some controversy with PoS.</p><p>The SEC once defined 66 cryptocurrencies as securities, including high-market-cap coins like SOL and ADA. However, ETH was not included, which gave many people hope and left ETH’s PoS in a somewhat ambiguous space.</p><p>A significant fact is that PoS is a permissioned consensus mechanism.</p><p>In PoS, nodes often need to stake a certain amount of tokens to become block-producing nodes, and staking these tokens is the entry barrier for PoS.</p><p>A node wanting to become a block-producing node needs to acquire many tokens. Where do these tokens come from? Either they are allocated by the project at the genesis stage or subsequently bought from miners because miners will increase the supply of tokens.</p><p>Here’s the problem: imagine an extreme scenario where all token holders are unwilling to sell their tokens. Wouldn’t the control of the entire network be in their hands? Whether they are ten people or ten thousand, it is still a closed circle. Moreover, in PoS, the more tokens you have, the greater your power, which further increases PoS’s centralization.</p><p>At this point, you might wonder, with Ethereum’s success and millions of holders, thousands of institutions managing tens of thousands of block-producing nodes, isn’t it decentralized enough?</p><p>Therefore, we must distinguish two concepts: a decentralized consensus mechanism and a decentralized blockchain. These are not the same.</p><p>Even if BFT-like consensus only supports a scale of dozens of nodes, if these nodes are distributed worldwide and held by large consortia with conflicting interests, the chain can still be considered decentralized because it is unlikely that more than two-thirds of these stakeholders will cooperate.</p><p>Similarly, Ethereum being decentralized does not mean PoS is a decentralized technology.</p><p>Why do many project teams choose PoS over PoW to issue coins? Because PoW is uncontrollable and has a high risk of being attacked. Observing the current PoW chains, almost all are forks of Bitcoin, and there are very few new ones. Most new altcoins come from Ethereum’s tech stack.</p><p>Why is PoS controllable? As long as you don’t distribute the initial funds too widely, you have control over the entire chain. Even if distributed, as long as the overall proportion is controllable, the chain remains under your control.</p><p>But then, isn’t the mining resource of Bitcoin also controlled by a few manufacturers? If they are unwilling to sell mining machines, Bitcoin would always be controlled within a certain range. Not exactly; even without advanced mining machines, you can still participate in mining. Accumulating many outdated mining machines can still yield high computational power. At least no one has the authority to deprive you of the qualification to become a block-producing node.</p><p>In contrast, PoS is different; without enough money, you do not qualify to become a block-producing node. If token holders are unwilling to sell, you cannot obtain this qualification no matter how much effort you put in. PoS is essentially a consensus mechanism where the door is closed, and everyone negotiates internally, randomly selecting a block-producing node among qualified nodes and then voting.</p><p>What if there is a PoS without an entry barrier? All nodes are block-producing nodes, and one is randomly selected each round to produce blocks. This mechanism would inevitably suffer from Sybil attacks, eventually becoming a game of competing node numbers. Competing node numbers are not necessarily bad, as the number of nodes ultimately reflects hardware resources. Nodes with more hardware resources have a higher chance of being selected. I think such a consensus mechanism has further room for thought, but it faces many practical issues, such as how to use VRF to select the next block-producing node and whether the required network bandwidth for such a large number of block-producing nodes is supported by existing technology. Also, a PoS without an entry barrier is not really PoS.</p><p>15 years have passed, and Bitcoin has never been surpassed…</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I want to compare PoW and PoS from the perspective of entry barriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often describe a blockchain as either permissionless or</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Consensus Mechanism" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/Consensus-Mechanism/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>What a Bull Market Means for the Average Person</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/03/13/What%20a%20Bull%20Market%20Means%20for%20the%20Average%20Person/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/03/13/What%20a%20Bull%20Market%20Means%20for%20the%20Average%20Person/</id>
    <published>2024-03-13T15:58:55.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-06T12:55:49.314Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you held some cryptocurrencies during the market downturn, the biggest significance of a bull market is that it allows your limited assets to gain in value.</p><p>If you are a Bitcoin believer, the biggest significance of a bull market is to prove that your faith is correct and that your foresight from a few years ago was valid. But that’s about it if you didn’t invest a lot of money back then.</p><p>Many people now regret not buying more Bitcoin at 38K when they see it at 70K. But a year ago, would you have dared to buy Bitcoin at 38K? Probably not. Who knew how much lower it could go at that time? If I told you Bitcoin would rise to 200K in a year, would you dare to buy it now? Still, probably not. It’s simple; no one can predict the future. Only in hindsight does everyone look like a stock market genius.</p><p>Recently, Bitcoin has trended on Weibo twice. People start paying attention when prices rise. I’ve also watched ETH drop from 3400 to 1800 and then climb back to 4000. But really, what kind of change does such volatility bring? Turning 10K into 20K? It doesn’t seem to mean much.</p><p>Bull markets are often accompanied by many get-rich-quick stories. In my understanding, there are several ways to make money:</p><ol><li><p>Trading, holding spot, and value investing. This is relatively stable with controlled risks but limited returns. How much you dare to invest depends on how much investable funds you have. Don’t be fooled by whales making millions; their actual assets are at least five times more than their investments. Similarly, the returns for ordinary people are limited. Betting your house on Bitcoin is gambling. Usually, people who make and lose a lot of money do so in a cycle. Only a few can stop at the right time, and those who can already have self-control beyond human nature.</p></li><li><p>Leveraging contracts. This type of trading should be done with small amounts, like 10 or 20 bucks for fun. If you want to make money, don’t touch it. You could lose all your money and not get it back. Market makers can do it if they can control the market, but that’s not for ordinary people.</p></li><li><p>Issuing meme coins. Jumping on the current trend, anything hot can be turned into a coin: AI coin for new AI tech, ROCKET coin if Musk tweets a rocket photo. There will always be players who buy for the hype. This method relies heavily on luck. Additionally, you need some operational and technical skills, like setting up trading pools and promoting on social media, along with some graphic design skills to create a decent logo.</p><p> Even if it’s not a meme coin, issuing a low-quality token can make money as long as people are willing to play and buy it. However, this requires some costs for technology, graphics, and operations. Many get-rich-quick stories stem from such coins. I’ve seen people succeed with this, but I don’t envy them because I know I can’t make that kind of money.</p></li><li><p>Phishing websites. This is outright illegal and requires hacking skills and experience, so it’s not an option.</p></li><li><p>Airdrop hunting. Now, airdrop hunters have turned it into a small industry, participating in early projects on a large scale. This is highly random and requires luck. Many people spent money on transaction fees and ended up with nothing. Moreover, it’s about the return on investment. Some airdrop hunters make millions on a single project, but they must have substantial assets to invest. Given the opportunity, most people wouldn’t have enough money to capitalize on it. I don’t engage much in airdrop projects, perhaps due to a lack of information.</p></li><li><p>DeFi. Earning yields by staking funds on platforms to earn interest. This carries the risk of the project rug-pulling, so you need to choose reliable projects.</p></li><li><p>MEV (Miner Extractable Value). This multi-billion-dollar market is already targeted by experienced players, and making money from it might require competing on speed.</p></li><li><p>Developing a technically demanding project and being a core developer, receiving initial token allocations and waiting for their value to multiply. This method is safer but rare, especially in the current market where few dare to start new developments. Most projects are integrations of existing technologies. Projects with significant contributions in specific technical directions are not only rare but also have high technical barriers, which are beyond the reach of ordinary people.</p></li><li><p>Regular work, steady job. Working in a crypto exchange is not much different from working in an internet company, with the main differences being the non-traditional office environment and getting paid in tokens.</p></li><li><p>Mining. Mining might not be profitable anymore.</p></li></ol><p>There are two types of bull markets: one driven by favorable policies leading to price increases, and another driven by new technologies attracting more players. The current bull market is the former. Besides crazy prices, no significant new technologies or phenomena have emerged. Apart from price changes, nothing else seems to have changed. Or, you could say, we’re still in the early stages of the bull market, and those who dare should quickly invest more :P</p><p>Another point is that a bull market attracts more capital, leading to more new projects and companies, possibly creating more job opportunities. Lately, some small, obscure companies have appeared, suggesting the job market might be slightly improving. However, these small companies likely work on the usual types of projects…working anywhere is the same. For those facing layoffs, the job market might feel a bit easier.</p><p>For the average person, the current bull market doesn’t seem to mean much. Tonight, Ethereum completed the Cancun upgrade, and it’s unclear if this will trigger another Layer 2 boom. I’m not much of an Ethereum believer; Layer 2 feels incomplete to me, and Ethereum now focuses on Layer 2 development. Similarly, some companies are working on Bitcoin Layer 2 projects, which I’m also not optimistic about. Bitcoin Core isn’t interested in scaling and could make BRC-20 projects disappear entirely.</p><p>So, should we believe in Bitcoin? It seems Bitcoin doesn’t relate much to the average person either. I hope a project representing faith will emerge.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you held some cryptocurrencies during the market downturn, the biggest significance of a bull market is that it allows your limited</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Cryptocurrency" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/Cryptocurrency/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Recent Work in the Past Six Months</title>
    <link href="https://en.smallyu.net/2024/02/17/Recent%20Work%20in%20the%20Past%20Six%20Months/"/>
    <id>https://en.smallyu.net/2024/02/17/Recent%20Work%20in%20the%20Past%20Six%20Months/</id>
    <published>2024-02-17T02:49:03.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-06T12:57:14.609Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The main work over the past six months has focused on three main tasks.</p><h4 id="Building-the-Abstract-Account-ERC-4337-Project"><a href="#Building-the-Abstract-Account-ERC-4337-Project" class="headerlink" title="Building the Abstract Account (ERC-4337) Project"></a>Building the Abstract Account (ERC-4337) Project</h4><p>An AA account is essentially a smart contract that implements features such as zero fees and social recovery through additional bundler and paymaster components. ERC-4337 defines a set of standards, including the interfaces that the contract must support, how the bundler interacts with the contract, and the role of the paymaster. Currently, there are roughly three to five different implementations for each component, with some variations in details, but all follow the ERC-4337 standard.</p><p>Last year, the concept of abstract accounts gained some popularity, possibly because Vitalik mentioned Soulbound. Project teams used AA accounts as a solution for Soulbound, creating some hype. Innovations like ERC-4337, which define standards rather than change the underlying technology, generally don’t have long-lasting impacts. It’s a series of standardized usage methods. While it might provide short-term solutions, it’s not a bad thing.</p><h4 id="Using-Op-Stack"><a href="#Using-Op-Stack" class="headerlink" title="Using Op Stack"></a>Using Op Stack</h4><p>Since Optimism open-sourced the entire Op Stack toolkit, launching an Optimistic Layer 2 has become easier. This led to the trend of one-click chain launches last year, with Base, opBNB, and others going live in a short period. Although Optimism’s Fault Proof is not yet perfect, even a slightly centralized project can be stable enough. The Op Stack can fully support launching your own network.</p><p>We ran AA accounts on a Layer 2 network, which supported a small gaming event. Despite some challenges along the way, we gained valuable experience. Diving deeply into these two types of projects is impossible within a limited timeframe, as each direction can be a specialized field. Currently, the status is barely usable.</p><p>However, have you noticed that concepts like AA accounts and one-click chain launches are short-lived? They were hot last year, but no one talks about them this year. This year, the focus has shifted to Bitcoin’s Layer 2, inscriptions, ERC-404, etc. Hot topics are always changing.</p><h4 id="Building-an-Ethereum-PoS-Network"><a href="#Building-an-Ethereum-PoS-Network" class="headerlink" title="Building an Ethereum PoS Network"></a>Building an Ethereum PoS Network</h4><p>Since The Merge, building the Ethereum network has become more complex. Although it saves the computational power consumption of mining, it requires the introduction of a complex validator governance mechanism to ensure orderly block production. PoS inevitably involves issues like becoming a validator and determining valid validators. Previously, nodes were divided into two types, execution layer and consensus layer. PoS solves the ungraceful block production issue of PoW, but at the cost of a complex set of rules.</p><p>Ethereum is currently the most diverse ecosystem chain, with five or six clients each for the execution layer and consensus layer, all implementing standard interfaces but with different experiences, especially in performance. A lot of time was spent testing each client.</p><p>Ethereum’s greatest asset is the EVM, not PoS. EVM compatibility has become a selling point for various chains. PoS was not invented by Ethereum; Cardano used PoS from the start and retained the UTXO model. Occasionally, people say Bitcoin and Cardano are the future. Compared to Ethereum, Cardano’s consensus mechanism is more like a Bitcoin alternative rather than Ethereum.</p><p>Bitcoin and Ethereum belong to two camps. Bitcoin focuses on cryptocurrency, while Ethereum explores applications beyond currency. Under each camp, many altcoins are active.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
        
        
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The main work over the past six months has focused on three main tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;Building-the-Abstract-Account-ERC-4337-Project&quot;&gt;&lt;a</summary>
        
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Work" scheme="https://en.smallyu.net/tags/Work/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
